before I forget I have two Corrections
from the last two
classes
uh okay uh one is um what Michael
corrected me on on that uh a does belong
if you split the LM lineages into two
starting from Lord Buddha then but St
the activity Lage which is called yin
cha comes down first to
Buddha and not I
said said and then he's I just give you
a funny look I didn't say word no but I
I heard it and uh and cuz you think it
would be CH but anyway it comes down to
my and into that's one correction uh
from the first class and then
um the second class as we mentioned I
think you mentioned
yesterday uh I discussed the I wrote the
traditional verse for the seven Diamond
like Visions then we discussed the
number of them and then we discussed the
order of them and it looked like the
order that came first and the order
during the order were
different uh and they are I mean I
checked the book and then g j says how
come they're different you know and um
he says you know you can do it either
way and that's in your first in your
second reading that you don't have yet
okay so um it was a good point El says
you could do it either way so either way
your homework is okay meaning uh
switching four and
five uh either way okay I mean I
remember getting up and saying it way G
said it and then thinking it that I lost
the logic at a certain point uh so we'll
do it again you know you want to become
a your own future Buddha so you could
teach your own future Dharma to turn
your own future uh direct realizers of
emptiness people into that right so that
covers the first three and then the
question is uh is between the Buddha
that you need to help you do that the
outside Buddha the one who already
exists and then the come or the Buddha
nature in you so with would that come
Buddha nature first and outside Buddha
first or outside Buddha first and Buddha
nature first and that's where the
question comes in some let me get it
straight some people say after the first
three you go find an outside Buddha who
inspires you to take your own inner seed
and and work on it some people say you
think about your own inner seed and want
to become a Buddha and then you go to an
outside Buddha who can teach you and
like that so either way you do on the
homework is fine something that you
would spend six hours debating in the in
the debate ground with no resolution
just for fun okay
uh so today we're on so we're going to
work slowly through the seven Diamond
like visions
which means first of all uh discussing
the three jewels right the three jewels
and and today I think we're going to
delve into the question of one of the
main topics today will be why when he
discussed the three
jewels did he choose the Buddha Dharma
and sa that you want to
become because they don't exist yet I
mean theoretically for most of us maybe
for me at least okay they don't exist
yet so I mean taking Refuge doesn't it
imply taking refuge in someone outside
of you uh and isn't that even part of
the definition you know you go to Refuge
to someone outside of you because of two
causes fear and you think they might be
able to help you right so why does he
start out calling the Buddha Dharma sa
that you are going to
become uh the three
jewels which are the objects of Refuge
right so we're going to go into that a
little bit today we have to
start
for for
good
morning
say
means no need to carve it just write
it okay sorry just kidding
I started out that
wayed Jaa is is an idiom in ched Jawa
means the the ideal or the one that the
teaching was meant for and dja means
student or disciple okay so this whole
phrase means a student that the utar
tant was meant for the student that the
utar tant was designed for
and you know that duel
means uh to discipline or to tame a a
wild horse for example it's called duel
so the word disciple is the same in
tibetan as it is in English disciple
meaning the one who needs to be
disciplined or tamed or
broken okay not fun but the result is
cool so CH means the ideal disciple or
the perfect disciple that this book was
meant
for um and this is very common in the
ancient teachings each book is designed
each teaching as you know from T is
designed for a particular group of
students it's like I used to play jazz
uh in college and all the the only jobs
we could get because we weren't that uh
normal was uh in this weird bar outside
of the college and um
and you would get up and then depending
on who was listening you would play
differently you see like you start a
song and then you see the reaction and
then if the audience feeds you back then
you go higher and higher and if they're
all just drinking and fighting and stuff
trying to get up on the stage you
know you your music actually goes to a
lower level because you're just trying
to read something in them right and it's
the same for a teacher as you know who
tried to teach you know you get up you
see how the eyes look you know or how
the body language is and then if it's
good you go higher and if it's not so
good you go down a few notches you know
and then that creates problems thousand
years later when they go through
Winston's teachings uh the videos you
know and they're like I don't get it you
know first he said this was true and
then two days later at a different
teaching he said something else was true
and that's why you get into fights about
CH or how to interpret what a teacher
said um so each major teaching or each
major book has the Lord Buddha or Lord
MRE in this case they have somebody in
mind for this book that's called
CH they write this book or they dictate
this book to
whom a into Shah heaven right and they
have people certain people in mind
certain people in mind
um so I'm going to tell you what that
kind of person is for this book because
it has to do with the first three
Diamond life visiones okay done
me
say take
Chin
T first part of a student for whom this
book was meant is that they must be t k
means
Mahayana uh big capacity people big
capacity Rick means type or family
richicken means uh belongs to the family
belongs to the type
right today you
have we've entered the family buddas
right um so first they should be a
Buddha BFA family in other words if
you're in this
room if you made it all the way out here
in the middle of
nowhere uh it's not by accident okay
it's by millions of lifetimes of praying
that you could learn this book okay it's
from millions of lifetimes of trying to
develop uh compassion for other people
or you wouldn't be here you wouldn't
karmically you wouldn't have made it
into this room uh so you have this
uh you are tunity to if you made it this
point you have deep within you a c or a
seed that wants to be able to serve
every living creature in many planets
countless planets so you have that uh
and that's the first part that makes you
able to sit here to be a student of this
class okay uh w
say wman w Wong means power I think you
know like a Wong is a is an initiation
is called Wong and then Wong means very
very Shar Powers meaning you have a high
Dharma
IQ and you know I've mentioned it many
times Wong noon doesn't mean uh worldly
IQ you know like you meet many people
who are very capable people very
intelligent in a worldly way very
capable they can do anything in business
and things like that but their drama IQ
can be
zero and then you meet other people who
have a high D IQ that can't like drive a
car or something like that you know like
just run into things and uh so and then
you mean many people have both actually
but what we're talking about is a high
Dharma IQ High Dharma iqq how does that
manifest itself I mean
um they believe higher things and they
they are motivated to do higher things
they they are faced with a lifetime of
consuming or a lifetime of trying to get
liberated and helping others in an
ultimate Way and they just naturally
gravitate towards the second okay does
that mean they don't have jobs no not
necessarily they could be president of a
big Corporation but they in the back of
their mind and in their heart their
motivation is always that they should do
this to help other people and then they
have this drive to learn the DH well
practice well meditate well Retreat well
so that makes them War them so you can
say high comp High Dharma IQ okay uh you
have to have this to be a student in
this class okay to be a student of the
utar Tantra
theas the ideal student the student for
whom this book was
designed are people who display two
qualities they they have like compassion
they are Mahayana family type of people
they have deep in their hearts the
belief that they could become the next
bu they could become my TR they will be
my TR they believe that and then
secondly they have this D High Dharma IQ
which is typified by being attracted to
Holy activities uh Meditation Retreat
study serving other people
okay that kind of person is ideal for
this book does that mean that other
people can't listen to this
book it's Tantra
secret Tantra yeah Tantra means secret
right the word means secret but it's a
self keeping secret right I mean you can
show a Ted book to somebody somebody
who's not hasn't had initiation can go
and Pi an a Ted book they just won't get
it like they'll write a PhD thesis about
it okay or manbe you know that's that's
not a Kev
right not everyone who writes a PhD thes
about bound is doing so for the wrong
reasons but I'm just saying in case okay
uh or they might just think it's crazy
or even dirty or wrong okay and so uh in
that way tantre is a secret which keeps
itself and in the same way uh teachings
on the higher way like something like
the utar Tantra people just wouldn't get
it they wouldn't be first of all most
people who didn't have come who didn't
who weren't this kind of student they
wouldn't be attracted to it you know you
can start up get up start to give a
lecture about it and maybe like fall
asleep or leave and not come back you
know or fight with you and then you know
and that's a very typical for someone
who isn't up to this level of student um
so in a way the books the secrets keep
themselves and it's not that Lord Buddha
said these students anybody who wasn't
the student couldn't come to that
teaching it was just that if they came
they weren't attracted to it or they
even heard a lower
teaching which is where the idea of
lower kinds of emptiness comes in in the
mindor school and in the lower half of
the middle high
school so that's the kind of student
that we would teach this book to
um then G goes on to say
that ideal student for this
book would uh be you could tell them
from three three different
characteristics so I'm going to go
through those three characteristics
these are the three that are on your
homework okay first one
say
good GBA means uh necessity necessity
this thing must happen this thing must
happen Okay the ideal student for this
scripture is ideal first of all says G
of J because they realize there's a g
something's got to happen what's that I
got to do something about all the pain
in the world I got to do something I
have to try to do something about all
the pain in the world okay there are two
qualities there inside gppa right these
are like subsets of gppa right um one
would be n
so the debate would go like this okay
it'd be like this uh I'll pick on M
already
uh well let you see what's the First
Quality that uh a disciple for for the
which the reti T was specifically
designed what's the First Quality they
should have belongs to Mar in general
yeah that's in general and then secondly
High spiritual IQ yeah High spiritual IQ
and then if the homework said now give
me the three or four qualities that they
have you go on to here so what would be
the first one compassion well it'd
Bea
is necessity yeah like they're driven
they say something's got to happen
something's going to
happen why are they driven they see
that's a the H thing why do they have
that first call driven because they got
n they got n what's n
karuna great compassion compassion okay
compassion difference from J how
anybody yeah one is wanting
to give them everything they need and
the other one's wanting to take all yeah
which one is this compassion to take
yeah so nin is driven by wanting to take
away other people's problems and then
Juma which happens to be the the name
for
MRE uh is wanting that after you take
away their trouble and give them
anything they want okay um but if you
ask me how come the ideal student for
retire time to recognizes some necess
something's going to happen well first
of all they have need okay first of all
they're worried about the suffering of
the world okay you wouldn't be in this
room if you weren't that okay you might
be in a New York class because some guys
walked in following the cute girls who
came to
class I won't name any
names who later became a very very fine
student uh yeah me uh but if you're this
far this not the you know you have some
concern you have some concern for other
people suffering okay and then B you
know this from last night
say Mercedes
um responsibility yeah personal
responsibility I'll do it myself we
talked about it last night with your uh
do good company right no one else helps
me I'll do it myself and you know you
don't have to go very far in the D
business before you bump into the
necessity of talk something
okay right uh AR with the uh with the
urit for example taking down the urits I
mean if you're going to do the taking
down the urits you got to decide if I'm
the last person out in this hell hole
taking them down I don't care I'm
sticking it out you know and for
that you got to have talkon okay talkon
means I'll do it myself you know and it
comes in the seven point uh seven steps
to developing body CH it's just before
you get body CH it's Last Thing Before
am I right yeah just before B each other
okay so if you're going to be the
student for whom this teaching was
meant yeah and we say what are the three
qualities and the first one is you see
some necessity going on you got to do
something okay what drives you to that
necessity karuna you see the suffering
of people you want to do something about
it some I'll be goddamn well do it
myself if nobody else helps me nobody
else pitches in everybody in the
Scriptures it says if everybody Rises
and becomes my enemy and tells me I'm
crazy and fights against me I don't care
I'll get it done I'll do it they'll take
me later okay talk some okay
uh now the second quality right of the
three okay first we had necessity and
not had under it these two qualities now
the second main
call what was that oh
am I on two or B two on two
okay this is where the homework gets
messed up
[Music]
usually
say right this s gets caused it to be
lengthened slightly
like n Nick would have
[Laughter]
a okaya means what
anybody ability the ability okay
potential
potential pull the I don't know which
one you know only BR into theone at the
bottom hopefully we'll forget to plug it
back in
uh NAA means
the the disciple For Whom the utar tant
was designed which is you
guys oh come on you're talking about the
early Indian disciples am
I my I can only
see
today you know me my my chair can't look
ahead 2,000 years and say
or 17700 years and say they're going to
be sitting there in East you know got to
get this ready for
them it's just as you're just as valid
as the first Disciples of that you are
you are CH of
the because you see the NAA having seen
the G you saw the necessity for
something to happen and now you see the
naaa means potential means it can happen
I see it can happen okaya means I not
only see it has to happen I see it can
happen and g j says to me I mean I get
Thrills up the back of my spine when I
read why he thinks n is
possible like you ideal student for this
book they see there's a potential for
buddhahood happening
because oops
this is a subset of yeah it's the reason
why there's n like the other two were
the reason why there'sa
they see there's potential because they
Pi emptiness yeah they perceive
emptiness okay because they perceive
emptiness okay I love that that's very
ACI that's very World okay they see
buddhahood is possible I mean one thing
they know it's got to be
done they say it's possible why because
they okay so you're
ready
sorry if someone is a perfect student
for
the right
it must have already
proceed
what because they see the potential for
Buddha they see it's possible and that's
only because say
G
that you contradict every scripture he
didn't say directly he just said I
didn't say he said directly and he
didn't say he said directly you're
thinking he said directly
no I thought I thought you were saying
he said I didn't said me
because so Tony so the in this room all
proceed
tin about so they're all irons
right
good so just because you perceive
emptiness doesn't mean you proceed
right Goa gotcha gotcha
doesn't mean you proceed a I didn't say
that no but you're right okay but that's
why you would screw the guy up again
yeah but anyway yeah it's not true that
just because you've seen emptiness
you've seen it
directly okay
so what GS up to that saying is very
powerful you can't be the ideal student
for this book if you don't grasp that
buddhahood is possible because you
understand you understand that your own
being is empty and that if you collected
the right cner by keeping your book
nicely your Val you would perceive that
empty screen as a as my
TR and and if you get it you know
everybody in this room gets that right
anybody who doesn't get it raise your
[Music]
hand you get that your own being is an
empty screen you get that if you keep
your vales do Retreats do meditation
help diamond mountain happen right for
others right you will will see this
being become my TR okay you get that so
you get the NAA you get the possibility
and that that's why you're the special
student for this book and that happens
to be why you end up in this room at
this moment okay and and that's the you
see the potential for becoming my tra
like people in this room didn't start
laughing when I said you're all going to
be my tra you know you're just kind
of wondering how it it's going to happen
but you understand the newa right you
know the potential you know the
potential and you're thinking well I cut
my meditation short this morning I
didn't do it at all uh you know you're
wondering how that's going to
happen you have to keep it up
okay
new third quality of that student
say top
to top
to J means
I'm going to do it I'm going to do it to
that's
to to to acheve achieve which so it
means what
to I'm going to achieve it I'm going to
do it you know damn it I'm going to do
it
to that comes
aftera and NAA righta this thing's got
to get
done NAA it's possible because things
are even empty to I'm going to do it I'm
going to attain I will be the next my
turn I'm sorry the
mat I will be my turn you have to think
like that okay my turn I will be my
turn pretty much we have already perfect
circumstances you have great trials
ahead of us to make this place happen uh
it's a lot of work for a few people
later people will come and complain
about the lemonade we said right and uh
but we the have to build the houses and
get the lemonade ready and uh so in a
way we have the most work to do but but
that's why you're here and you're a toer
JW type of person you know I'll get it
done I'll do it toer JW Okay g j throws
in a fourth quality
okay where do the three come from if you
you throws in a for you'll see why
you'll see why oops let me see how to
spell it exactly
oh
okay for
say they ain't
men DH intellect what's
t
d d d actually okay they are not Dull
Dharma IQ dull spiritual intellect
okay and then g j goes on to say what
does it mean to be a Dharma Demi okay
what does it mean it means saying to
without
saying it's it's number three without
number one and number two
topa without GBA and which means oh I'll
attain Buddha hood for all living beings
without saying that there's a necessity
and without seeing how it's going to
happen and that's what makes
you a less qualified student for this
book okay like oh you run around saying
you're a Buddhist you run around saying
you know I'm I'd like to be a Buddhist
I'd like to do buddh but you don't
really appreciate how much the world is
suffering and you don't really
appreciate that it's totally possible
because I'm empty okay you got to have
those two or else you're a wrong D okay
you you're doing it without really
understanding it and that makes you what
they call dull dull faculties okay and I
think uh personally that you guys have a
you've been through so many classes on
Karma and emptiness that you really
really get the newart I think that's
where most people I think
every person outside of Tibetan India
who is attracted to Buddhism in my
experience 95% of them are coming
because someone close to them died they
saw some terrible accident they
themselves had cancer you know they've
seen suffering and then they turned to
the DH but it's the NAA part where
people fall right it's the nupa part
like they kind of dimly understand
that there was a Buddha and that you
know probably I can become a Buddha but
they are more in this mindset of a
Buddha like God you know and that's a
very um big difference between that what
the religion I grew up with and and the
Dharma I came to embrace you know God is
outside of you God you cannot become God
to say you could become God would be
almost irreverent or Blasphemous
Blasphemous but in Buddhism the whole
point is quite different and isn't it
quite different in which
book it starts out with three three
Diamond like visions of what the future
your future right that's the whole point
that's why g j is rubbing in this thing
this whole book starts out you don't go
to Refuge to Buddha dharman who are in
India 2 and a half thousand years ago
you don't go to Refuge to some Buddhist
monks who have the funny looking eyes
and different uh culture uh drink salty
tea and bang on weird drums and stuff
you don't go to refuge in that you're
going the highest student a student of
highest intellect is going for refuge in
in what F their own buddhahood what they
will become for the world and that's
really powerful that's really powerful
so you're not this kind of wrong tool
you totally see how it's possible and
that's totally the goal of your life and
as we're about to see in this class for
G of J that's what refuge
means that's what refuge means that's
why he put the three jewels first and
that's why the three jewels are the ones
that you're going to
become okay for him that's the whole
point of of religion is to worship the
thing you're going to become and to
strive towards that and to see the newa
see how it's going to happen because you
are empty okay so it's not like in in
this class for people of your
intellectual capacity right I wouldn't
say this out in uh Joo Baptist Church
when Mercedes and and Christie and I go
to do our presentations there we're not
going to you know uh what do you call
emphasize that the goal of this class is
that you become God or something like
that not at the beginning any okay but
uh but it's very appropriate in a class
of CH people who are special disciples
you know you are you grasp the need and
you grasp the possibility because you
understand emptiness okay and and you
have
n so therefore you don't qualify as one
of these dollar intellect students and
you now got a taste for why the first
three of the seven Diamond Visions are
the three jewels that you are going to
become okay
uh let me see what comes
next this is a part that I really like
um of the retire temp
and here I'm going to put the Sanskrit
since you guys learned Sanskrit today
your s teacher will go over why it looks
funny okay when two continents bump
together in Sanskrit they create a new
letter unfortunately okay so this is the
T and this is the n but anyway it turns
out right now okay
as we said in the yoga teaching ratna
comes from R
ra which ultimately means to give or
bestow or of value came into Latin as
aace and into their English word reality
meaning something real something of
value something substantial okay
um and the toban chose to translate as
coino say coino Co this is like the only
word in tibetan where you have this
thing called Tong where you saying oi
sound O Like O right uh so it should be
should have been
pronounced but just by because of some
historical accident this single word is
pronounced coin choke say coin coin coin
um when you treat it by itself
it's kba means rare
rare okay so this one means
rare CH means what supreme Supreme
nice it's getting harder to teach you
guys you
know three years ago you weren't as you
put a little heat on me okay coin coin
means uh rare choke means Supreme now
this is called the older period of
translation into
V it occurred I I believe the line
dividing line is
before long Dharma long Dharma was a
king who destroyed Buddhism in Tibet
just after it got started and then they
had to start over again but in the early
translation period the Tibetans were
very uh creative in translating Sanskrit
and then they would make up words like
uh money which literally means The
Silent One God translated pel's what in
the back seat of the car there in flag
St yeah good
guess CH which means the one who
defeated the enemy possesses the
qualities and has gone beyond
Transcendent you know it's this long
they just stuck together a bunch of
words and made a new word you know qu J
is one of those like the word for the
three jewels
traa in in tibetan is the rare Supremes
it sounds like Diana Ross and I used to
translate as rare Supremes but then
people gave me make fun of me so I
changed it to three JS but
um Studio outakes yeah yeah yeah yeah
recipe but these are um this is the word
for like quum would be
what and when it'sand gets mad they
say you know it's like Jesus
Christ it's funny like the first few
times you hear it you're
[Music]
like that's funny so now you know what
to say when you get man
in of course you shouldn't say
that now I always wondered why they
called it how did they get the coin how
did they get the chunk you know like is
that just something they made out and
what's cool is that the OT Tantra says
you should translate as coin joke you
know the Tantra says the three jewels
are and they're choke and coin choke is
not a bad way to translated so the
Tibetans were actually taking it from
this scripture and that to me that's
really exciting to see so you'll have
the roote text in your um reading and uh
it's it's a verse in the temp but my tra
gives six reasons why the jewels are and
why they're choke and I thought we'd go
that through that for
fun because I think we'll go through
half the six then take a break and then
come through the other half six reasons
why they're Supreme yeah and and why
they're rare you know why are the three
jewels which is
who you got go me me okay like we're not
just going through this for fun because
there six categories and gup is like
categories and you like that okay it's
like these are six qualities you're
going to have these are six qualities
that apply to you and you have to think
about them okay you have to become coino
the whole point of the first three
Diamond Visions you have to become the
three jewels so let's see what you got
to become why are you going to be rare
why are you going to be Supreme first
reason uh
you
[Music]
say see when when coin when the K gets
cut off of coin you don't say coin
anymore you say okay so that's why it's
not coin J means J means
happens means
only rely
okay in Sanskrit and IR was interested
about the it's
Dura which we studied we were we were
memorizing a text and it said that
people who can do a full Lotus for a
long period of time are
Dura in the loc Loca meaning
what hard to find d means hard to come
by okay yeah hard to come by you know we
experience
that we' seen life we could do it for an
hour an hour and a half two
hours long
story so J means doesn't happen very
often only rarely happens and then g j
says most people in the entire world
don't have the Kwa to see the three
jewels they don't have the Kwa to ever
run into the three JS what's
Kwa Good Karma good coming you know they
just don't have it they are like the
people in the town that aanga ran into
carrying my trail on his shoulders and
what did they see nothing mostly nothing
yeah mostly nothing okay they just just
crazy guy I mean every time I feel like
I'm getting called crazy too much I
think of a AA running around town with
my TR something and it comforts me you
know so like okay they just couldn't see
anything you know they said so they said
you know they probably would have locked
him up in nowadays right he's running
around town screaming about this guy in
his show yeah they would have so
Jun uh Jun means the three jewels happen
only rarely in the world meaning listen
they here all the time but people can't
see it cuz they don't have to kill and
people don't meet them and people don't
run into
them I was to give me a look like are
they here all the time good debate are
they here all the time
[Music]
who's proceeding oh good nice who's
proceeding good very nice it's it's
actually a sort of a self-existent thing
it's an error of world view to say
they're here all the time that's like
saying my llama is really a temp
da yeah it's an error in worldview to
say that but like emptiness there really
what I don't perceive emptiness but
everything has its own emptiness it's
there regardless of my perception so the
bud I thought we talk about this a
couple times last week
I I don't have to directly perceive an
object's emptiness to understand that it
has an emptiness so I don't have to
directly to see a Buddha in the room to
to suppose that there's a bud on every
Adam uh you guys debated in the debate
ground okay and there should be a debate
ground here we will have a debate ground
and that will be one of the main reasons
to be a
it will
be you guys discussing with each other
once a week right yeah at least all day
okay yeah you can do it in the car you
can do it while you're working you can
do it anytime but you got to do it it's
100% difference the people in the S
class I think realize that you know like
you if you just talk it over with
somebody in plain normal English for 20
minutes while you're washing dishes or
something it just sticks in your mind
really good later uh in the fall 2004 it
will be a requirement to debate why
um between classes okay so I'll move out
before that
anyway uh second
quality what is the second
[Music]
you
say
Chim in Sans near Mala and you'll go
over there with you if you want to in
your Sanskrit class Beau class but uh CH
means impurity or stink and may means no
no stink okay so it means spotless or
unpolluted or uh untain
like
that the Sanskrit near Mala the Mala has
come into English as in what word can
you guess something that means bad Mal
content Mal content malevolent
malnutrition meaning bad like m in it's
French does it mean
bad so it's like that yeah ultimately it
probably relates to Mor also yeah so it
just means bad
um not bad no no Steam and then G is a
very interesting thing you know you can
get these books where they say all the
bu is immaculate and wonderful and
therefore to me okay that's say just
no they are Immaculate in the sense that
they don't
have what should we saying
uh I remember one
of um
they they don't have two
imperfections they are free of two
imperfections okay first one is of being
unable to protect
you and to me that's very profound you
know like
uh like I met a person in the last week
who's dying you know I asked
specifically to talk to them because I
know they're dying I mean very shortly
dying and they all know it everyone
knows it and um
so you want to offer them some
protection right I mean it's it's too
late actually it's too late to do
anything uh it hasn't happened yet but
but the time it takes to
practice the open teachings time it
takes to practice the secret teachings
the time it takes to master the inner
channels the work with the chakras the
time it takes to build up that inner
body with very difficult practices
there's just no time the person could go
into Retreat now and it's too
late
uh so there's all these worldly kinds of
protection that they're going to you
know oh I went to a specialist I had my
entire blood taken out screened radiated
put back into my body you know I had uh
now the person is going to um Faith
Heist because now after that process
Western scientist said forget it
um and there's and that protection is
going to let the person down but it has
Chima it's not Chim you see can't help
them won't help they'll die soon can't
protect them it's not a kind of
protection going to that kind of
protection uh even medicine surgical
procedures you
know uh they can't protect
you and they f the second one is Lua
they fail they they let you down Lua
means they fail you you always hear this
thing the three jewels are uniring
what's uniring me you know like they
don't make mistakes on their computer or
something uh it doesn't mean that air in
the Tibet and Lua means they let you
down they let you down people put their
hopes in money you know you're very
aware of security when you're out doing
a three-year retreat in the desert you
just become very aware of security
there's there were two rattlesnakes
Under Our Deck
a lot during most of the retreat you
know uh we were just out in the open
like if any Intruder came like Hunters
were wandering around one one Retreat
and almost got shot by a
hunter uh and then uh there were like U
drug Runners coming through the property
at the beginning and you had this you
just felt like being out there in the
middle of nowhere with no money no place
to buy anything uh no clothes we didn't
have you know we just had one pair of
clothes clothes or two pair of clothes
like you just feel this very thing that
you're not secure you don't have
security and then you're you in the
beginning of the retreat you have this
hunger for a job and this hunger for a
family and this hunger for the ability
to talk to friends or at least to
consume something like french fries
milkshake TV show latest video new CD
you just consuming makes you feel like
you're somebody you know consuming makes
you feel like you have some security you
take that away from people they almost
went crazy we almost went crazy you know
and what she comes to is you don't have
any security and this t means this this
coin CH that kind of security doesn't
let you down it's the only real security
you have emptiness and the perception of
emptiness and the possibilities raised
by that newa is the real only the real
only security the only real security
that we have okay the rest is all just
apparent you know the person I talked
about has
Extreme has access to great amounts of
money and there's there no security
okay so really to be able to live in
that ambiguity ambiguity where you don't
have any apparent security is a good
Buddhist trait it's a good Buddhist
trait you know it's
uncomfortable in some ways but in
another way you're not lying to yourself
you know there is no other security
and don't forget that we're talking
Security in the sense of what you will
become you know you will become someone
who doesn't let other people down
doctors let other people down lawyers
let other people down firemen let other
people down police let other people down
people who don't really understand
emptiness and karma let other people
down you want to become a refuge it
doesn't let other people down and that's
why you want to become the three jeels
did you have a question yeah is there
something significant in the way you
phrased um they don't have the
imperfection of being unable to protect
you as opposed to saying they have the
ability to protect oh yeah no well just
that in the root text it says they don't
have this bad quality you see of not
being able to do something so it's a
double negative rather than a positive
but that's the way Lord M did it now if
you went to the biground you could ask
people why did he say to me why didn't
he just say uh they something POS
you could debate that with
somebody I think the implication is that
other refugees do have
two if you think about it it's a myang
God there's a there's an implication
that there are other kinds of Refuge
which do let you down and which uh what
was the first
one unable to protect you okay same
thing really we'll do the third one and
then we'll take a
break Sarah took a break
ony you said two
yeah one was not being able to protect
others and second was letting people
down in this and often times that means
like inconsistent
results inconsist like you can't trust
what's going to
happen for
say
two then two and then this particular
combination of letters which you'll
learn in your Tibetan class is uh what
we call prenal so you don't say just
then you
say say so when you stick what we call
an open vowel which means an a e e a o
at the end of a s before an end sound it
gets really strong tund like gundan
there's no n in the word g in the middle
of the word g it's just what we call
this this prenasal effect like you know
this n effect okay so so you say t say
t uh two means power in the sense of
magnificent fantastic Mystic
power okay it's a very beautiful
word to do a two on somebody means to
curse somebody to g means to put a curse
on or spell on somebody
okay if you see P's pictures in his
early life he's like this thin handsome
guy if you see his pictures in his later
life he's like raed 300 lb or something
and they say two Gap somebody did a two
gap on him he he had like a spiritual
fight like a wizard with some evil
forces and he won but at out cost and
they were able to toap him and then then
he just he almost died like his body
just totally changed and um that's
called to
so tund means the three jewels have this
incredible Mystic Force Mystic
power
uh here um GJ starts actually in the
last one and the second one he starts
calling the three jewels he doesn't call
them Co he calls them y what's y
what's chint what's it mean what's chint
mean means M my go chint means wish
whatever you wish for whatever you could
think of so chint Mani means a wish
giving JY and this is a story in Tibet
and India that chintamani means there's
a special Jewel that if you find it and
then you put it through this washing
process like uh you have to wash it like
rock tumbling but some kind of Mystic
Waters like you know like holy water and
you have to bathe it in this holy water
and then you dry it off and then you
bathe it again and then you dry it off
and then you bathe it again you do all
these bathing rituals then you have to
set it in a special place like on the
top of a a flag pole called the to and
then you have to pray to it and you have
to do certain rituals and then it
becomes a wishing J so at this point G
of J starts talking about wishing Jewel
and he mentions when you say Chim which
means
what no more stain no imperfection he
says see the wishing jewels start to
wash we starting to wash this wishing
Jewel wishing Jewels have been well
washed and they also have two they have
two why why do they have some fantastic
power wishing a normal wishing
Dr give you they give you anything you
want it's like an alad lamb you know the
genie comes out you rub it the genie
comes out you say I want a big lemonade
for break you know
because they have M du du means there's
six kinds of Clairvoyance six kinds of
Clairvoyance the most important of which
is Shena which means uh the perfect
ability to read other people's
minds perfect ability to read other
people's
minds and I said you know like I think
in the retreat one of the main results
of the threee retreat was interesting
like I don't claim and it's that we all
could read uh what chiil was thinking
about on their grocery list for that day
you know what I mean but I'd say that
everybody in the threeyear retreat got
this very marked ability to sense the
emotions of the World At Large and of
the people around the retreat area you
know and especially the other Retreat I
mean if one Retreat and had a bad night
and couldn't sleep none of us could
sleep you know like after a certain time
it wasn't like you could read their
thoughts or you could hear oh man I
having a B night or something like that
but you just felt uneasy and you
couldn't sleep and then you'd find out
you know and then we start to place BS
of who was it you know and then next
time we saw him at the break we like
September 4th you
[Music]
remember
uh but you can develop this you know if
you do good Retreat if you do sincere
meditation if you keep your practice
well you start to get it and then by the
time you become a a jewel one of the
three jewels you have a perfect ability
to read other people's minds and the
idea is there that you can see their Cal
directly what's come nature yeah and
come can also mean their deep
propensities deep propensities right you
can look at a student and say okay this
student needs this right now and it
might be a Bop on the
head okay and and once you get to be a
once your abilities get Advanced like
that then you might start acting Strang
toward student you know it might seem
strange to other people but you see the
calm in them you see what their
propensity deep deep deep seeds are and
then you're more able to do
things that they
need and those won't be perceived by
other people and you will look strange
you know your activities or your your
behavior towards them might seem strange
uh and that's why you get stories like
Mara or um you know doing they just or
even Lam
or they just they're operating on a
different perception of a person's means
because they see them much deeper and
then they're they might be doing like
unusual Tuk skillful means to to help
that
person and if you don't have that you
can't be a good Tre Jewel so it's one of
the things you have to start thinking
about you have to start thinking to to
stop relating to people on a superficial
level you know oh this person looks like
they need need a Coke right now or this
person wants me to be nice to them right
now and you have to look deeper into
their needs way down into their needs
and see what they need right then and
sometimes it's
hard and the great num is I think like
Kim R he's not afraid to do something
that's very hard on his student I mean I
can speak from experience having been
the object for 20 years uh out of their
compassion um and seeing your come uh
they often ask you to do things that are
very difficult for you and and which
might even seem strange and then you
know 15 years later you're telling your
students how great it was that this LL
did this to you you know which I'm doing
okay so uh but you should pray to gain
that ability it's like on the list of
it's on your list of things to develop
the ability to see deep within a student
and see their real propensities and
their real needs where can you hook them
you know where can you turn where's the
Crux in their spirit that you can turn
and turn it up and and make them a
better person it help them become a
Buddha faster and sometimes it's a very
unusual thing
right uh we'll take a break and then
we'll finish yeah um CLA Bo is having to
do with one of the six Powers understood
but I'm not sure how the six Powers tie
in with t yeah t means powerful t means
powerful in the sense that they have the
six kinds of clairvoyants the most
important which of possess these six
Powers Yeah the most important of which
is uh the ability to read other people's
minds okay we'll take a break
come take a
[Music]
nice for